Daf is כז Kaf Zayin 27. Let's pick up right at the
top. משנה, Mishna, we're continuing to figure out the parameters of what
type of שבועה Shvuah you're חייב Chayiv or not חייב Chayiv for.
Again the specific context is what do you call it? Whether you
bring a קרבן, Korban, but in some of these, you know, it's
relevant issues also to a question about whether the שבועה Shvuah takes
effect altogether. So we've had the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael whether you're חייב Chayiv a קרבן Korban
for a שבועה Shvuah in the past, although everybody would agree that
if you did it מזיד Mazed intentionally, you would get מלקות, Lakkos,
that's a traditional שבועת שוא. Shvuat Shav.
And
then the משנה Mishna discussed the issue about well that everybody agrees
that a שבועה Shvuah has to be able to be for a
קרבן Korban has to be able to be said in the positive
and in the negative.
And yes and then we discussed also some differences between שבועות Shvuos
and
נדרים. Nedarim. And also the case that a שבועה בשוגג, Shvuah Bishogeg,
what constitutes a שבועה Shvuah in the past בשוגג. Bishogeg. You would
have thought that it would be a case of you just not
knowing, just thinking you were saying the truth, but the גמרא Gemara
actually frames that as an אונס, Anus, and which is fascinating. When
you think you're telling the truth, and תוספות Tosfos says that's not
only for קרבן, Korban, it's also for מלקות Lakkos and so on.
So the example of שוגג Shogeg it had basically was that you
didn't think it was so prohibited or you didn't think it would
end up in a קרבן. Korban. And then finally the last thing
we did yesterday, important thing, is that a שבועה Shvuah is not
binding until you actually express it out loud: לבטא בשפתים, Levatay Bisifatayim,
you enunciate it. And then became the question what types of things
might be binding if you just say them to yourselves, you know,
you just say them in your mind or as the גמרא Gemara
says in your heart. It talks about תרומה Trumah and קדשים, Kodshim,
but the interesting like קדשים Kodshim not if you actually say this
is a קרבן, Korban, this is an עולה, Olah, that you'd have
to say out loud, but you accept upon yourself the obligation to
give an עולה, Olah, and then the sort of remaining practical question
is what if you accept upon yourself to give a donation like
to the shul and you say I hereby am accepting upon myself
בנדר BiNeder whatever, whatever you say, I you know to give $180
to the shul, like is that binding without enunciating it? That's an
interesting discussion in the פוסקים. Poskim. So a lot actually that was
one place where I had actually a lot of contemporary potential contemporary
relevance. Yes. What if you're gonna fast the next day, does that
have to stay out loud? Yeah, so something like a fast you
would have to say out loud. You know, pretty much the general
rule is you have to say it out loud, you know, that's
that's the basic פשט. Pshat. You know, does it still take effect
if you said it to yourself? No, no, no, meaning if you
don't say it out loud, it's not effective. Yes. So what about
if I say something like I'm gonna give 180 million dollars to
the shul? Does that? Right, well we have to have דעת Da'at
to be גמר דעת. Gmar Da'at. Okay so now we turn to
the next משנה Mishna on כ"ז עמוד א'. Kaf Zayin Amud Aleph.
נשבע לבטל את המצוה, Nishba Livateil et HaMitzvah, we've already seen this,
right? Even though everybody agrees that the minimum things that a, you
know, that we're excluding from the קרבן, Korban, right, is the idea
of לבטל את המצוה. Livateil et HaMitzvah. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
we basically include everything. So what do we exclude from a קרבן?
Korban? When you're being when you take a שבועה Shvuah to be
מבטל את המצוה. Mevatel et HaMitzvah. That's clearly the one thing that
you know you would say should never, you know, cannot take effect
to begin with. Again maybe you get מלקות Lakkos for שבועת שוא,
Shvuat Shav, but it can't take effect to begin with. Nobody thinks
that's gonna be binding that you could obligate yourself to violate a
מצוה. Mitzvah. Okay ולא ביטל, v'Lo Bitel, so if you didn't go
ahead and מבטל, Mevatel, פטור, Patur, you're exempt from this קרבן Korban
because the שבועה Shvuah did not take effect. Okay לקיים ולא קיים,
Lekayem v'Lo Kiyem, how about you took a שבועה Shvuah to fulfill
a מצוה? Mitzvah? Is that binding? So פטור, Patur, that you're also
exempt. Why? You know so שהיה דין שיהא חייב, Shehaya Din Sheyehei
Chayiv, actually it would have stands to reason that you should be
obligated כדברי רבי יהודה בן בתירה KiDivrei Rabbi Yehuda Ben Batera and
it should like as and that is actually the position of רבי
יהודה בן בתירה. Rabbi Yehuda Ben Batera. What is this position of
רבי יהודה בן בתירה? Rabbi Yehuda Ben Batera? אמר רבי יהודה בן
בתירה, Amar Rabbi Yehuda Ben Batera, מה אם הרשות שאינו מושבע עליו
מהר סיני הרי הוא חייב עליו, Mah im haReshut she'eino Mushba Alav
meHar Sinai harei hu Chayiv Alav,
so what's the story when something is descre- like is a neutral
activity that you don't are not foresworn from הר סיני Har Sinai
to do it? And then if you negate it you are חייב.
Chayiv. So מצוה שהוא מושבע עליה מהר סיני, Mitzvah she'hu Mushba Aleha
meHar Sinai, let's say you take an oath to sit in a
סוכה. Sukkah. So you're already obligated. So now you're doubly obligated, right?
That should just give more weight to that oblig- to your שבועה.
Shvuah. Cause you're already obligated from הר סיני. Har Sinai.
אינו דין שיהא חייב עליה, Eino Din sheyehei Chayiv Aleha, how much
more so should you be חייב? Chayiv? אמרו לו, Amru Lo, they
said to him, לא, Lo, no, no, not necessarily or not not
necessarily, no! אם אמרת בשבועת הרשות שכן עשה בהן לאו
כהן, Im Amarta biShvuat haReshut sheken Asa baHen Lav keHen, remember the
one requirement we all sort of agreed upon or thought we all
agreed upon was להרע או להיטיב, Lehara o Leheitiv, that you have
to be able to say it in the positive and the negative.
Okay? So
that you can do by a normal type of neutral activity. But
תאמר בשבועת מצוה שלא עשה בה לאו כהן? Tomer biShvuat Mitzvah shelo
Asa ba Lav keHen? But by a case of שבועת מצוה Shvuat
Mitzvah we just you agreed that you can't take a שבועה Shvuah
to not sit in a סוכה. Sukkah. So therefore the שבועה Shvuah
to sit in a סוכה Sukkah is also not binding because at
least it doesn't lead to an obligation of a קרבן. Korban. קרבן
korban. *korban*. Okay, שנשבע לבטל ולא ביטל פטור *she-nishba l'vateil v'lo biteil
patur*, because you agreed at the first point that if you took
an oath to negate you can't negate, so therefore if you took
an oath to fulfill a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, you also do not
bring a קרבן korban. *korban* because it is not לאו והן lav
vehein, *lav ve-hein*. Now, if you remember earlier the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
said that רבי יהודה בן בתירא Rabbi Yehuda Ben Beseira *Rebbi Yehuda
ben Beteira* therefore implicitly rejects this requirement that something be able to
be framed as לאו והן lav vehein *lav ve-hein*. That would not
be a requirement for him to bring a קרבן korban, *korban*; it's
not somehow that מצוות mitzvos *mitzvot* are an exception, at least the
way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understood it earlier, he basically rejects this
as part of the obligation for bringing a קרבן korban *korban* that
you be able to frame it in the לאו והן lav vehein.
*lav ve-hein* frame. Now, what's interesting is is that the reason the
rabbis say that you don't bring a קרבן korban *korban* is because
you can't make it into the negative. But earlier, the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* said the reason that you don't bring a קרבן korban *korban*
when you take a שבועה shevuah *shvua* on something that you're already
obligated is because of the phrase used in the משנה mishna. *Mishna*:
מושבע ועומד מהר סיני mushba veomed mehar Sinai *mushba v'omed mehar sinai*.
אין שבועה חלה על שבועה ein shevuah chala al shevuah. *ein shvua
chala al shvua*, that a שבועה shevuah *shvua* doesn't take effect on
another שבועה shevuah *shvua*. So how come here we're framing it as
a type of a לאו והן lav vehein *lav ve-hein* argument? Now,
you could always say that they're saying that, you know, according to
the position of רבי יהודה בן בתירא *Rebbi Yehuda ben Beteira*, you
רבי יהודה בן בתירא *Rebbi Yehuda ben Beteira* think that מושבע ועומד
mushba ve'omeid. מהר סיני *mushba v'omed mehar sinai* is more of a
reason to be חייב chayav, *chayav*, that, you know, so even according
to your logic though, they're not חייב chayav. *chayav* because it can't
be reframed as a negative. Okay, but maybe, yes, one of the
reasons that this is also not binding is because you're מושבע ועומד
mushba ve'omeid, *mushba v'omed*. That's possible. But תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* has a
very interesting read of this משנה Mishna *Mishna*, which depends on a
גירסא girsa *girsa* question. Okay, and if you look back at the
beginning of the משנה Mishna, *Mishna* where it says, לקיים ולא קיים
פטור *lekayem v'lo kiyem patur*, שהיה בדין שיחייב כדברי רבי יהודה בן
בתירא *she-haya badin she-yechayev ki-divrei Rebbi Yehuda ben Beteira*, he takes out
one letter. The one letter תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* takes out is, or
he says actually this is the original גירסא *girsa*, the one letter
he says doesn't belong there is the כ *kaf*, כדברי רבי יהודה
בן בתירא *ki-divrei Rebbi Yehuda ben Beteira*. And it would read the
following: נשבע לקיים ולא קיים פטור *nishba lekayem v'lo kiyem patur*. Okay,
if you swore to fulfill and you didn't fulfill, you'd be exempt.
שהיה בדין שיחייב *she-haya badin she-yechayev*, logically you should be חייב chayav
*chayav*, but no, you're exempt. דברי רבי יהודה בן בתירא *divrei Rebbi
Yehuda ben Beteira*. This is the opinion of רבי יהודה בן בתירא
*Rebbi Yehuda ben Beteira*. And what רבי יהודה בן בתירא *Rebbi Yehuda
ben Beteira* is saying though, normally I say when you take a
שבועה shevuah *shvua* to fulfill a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, it would be
binding, if you take,
in this case it's not clear what the different case is, there
are cases he says when I concede that actually if you take
a שבועה shevuah *shvua* to fulfill a מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*, you'd be
פטור *patur*. What is the difference? So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says the
basic difference is, are we dealing with a negative מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah*
or a positive מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*? Are we dealing with like this
piece of חזיר *chazir* or נבלה neveila. *nevela*? If I take a
שבועה shevuah, *shvua* not to eat it, he says רבי יהודה בן
בתירא *Rebbi Yehuda ben Beteira* agrees that that שבועה shevuah *shvua* does
not take effect. Why? אין שבועה חלה על שבועה ein shevuah chala
al shevuah *ein shvua chala al shvua*, אין איסור חל על איסור
ein issur chal al issur. *ein issur chal al issur*. Remember that
we dealt with before? This thing is already a forbidden piece of
meat. If I try to say a שבועה shevuah *shvua* I won't
eat it, because of its state of forbiddenness, right? אין איסור חל
על איסור ein issur chal al issur. *ein issur chal al issur*,
איסור issur *issur* is state of forbiddenness. Then therefore it won't become
forbidden a second time. רבי יהודה בן בתירא *Rebbi Yehuda ben Beteira*
agrees to that. So the first part of the משנה *Mishna*, תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot* says, is רבי יהודה בן בתירא *Rebbi Yehuda ben Beteira*
himself is saying, look, I say if you take a שבועה shevuah
*shvua* to sit in a סוכה sukkah, *sukkah*, it is binding. You're
doubly obligated. You can be doubly obligated to do something. Okay, but
I, there's a case I agree that you'd be exempt. You can't,
if you can't be doubly forbidden, אין איסור חל על איסור ein
issur chal al issur. *ein issur chal al issur*, אין שבועה חלה
על שבועה ein shevuah chala al shevuah *ein shvua chala al shvua*.
Okay, so if you take a שבועה shevuah *shvua* to make this
case, to make this piece of meat forbidden, רבי יהודה בן בתירא
*Rebbi Yehuda ben Beteira* said, I'd agree you'd be exempt. It does
not become doubly forbidden. Okay, but if you take a שבועה shevuah
*shvua* to do, to actively do a positive מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* like
to sit in a סוכה sukkah. *sukkah*, he says there I say
that you are obligated because you can't, you can't be doubly forbidden,
that's אין איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur. *ein issur
chal al issur*, אין שבועה חלה על שבועה ein shevuah chala al
shevuah. *ein shvua chala al shvua*, but you can be doubly obligated.
So that is very nice within תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot* to think about
the distinction of those two. And it also helps to explain why
the rabbis said the idea of לאו והן lav vehein *lav ve-hein*.
Because when you're talking about making something forbidden, you can use the
language of אין איסור issur חל chal על איסור issur. *ein issur
chal al issur* or אין שבועה חלה על שבועה ein shevuah chalah
al shevuah. *ein shvua chala al shvua*. That's a principle that something
does not get a double status of forbiddenness. But when you are
talking about obligating yourself to sit in a סוכה sukkah. *sukkah*, maybe
אין שבועה חלה על שבועה ein shevua chala al shevua *ein shvua
chala al shvua* doesn't work. Why can't I be obligated from the
תורה Torah *Torah* and obligated from the, from my שבועה shevuah, *shvua*?
Fine, I'm doubly obligated, right? It makes more, it's something that we're
more, so in that case of doing a positive מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*,
maybe the only reason you're exempt is because of the idea of
לאו והן lav vehein. *lav ve-hein*, that you can't reframe it as
a negative. Alright, so everybody gets that? That's really worth, it's an
important conceptual point. I just see now
actually I have to break into the original and that should be
here. Now, oh,
I see I have paper towels over there. See, I don't know,
like paper towels have better sound. Okay,
so
if here's my little... piece of נבלה, okay, and then I say
the guy says שבועה shevuah
I won't eat נבלה. So what I want is I want this
thing, this is already איסור issur number one and now I want
it to become איסור number two. Okay, I want it to be
doubly אסור. assur. Okay, so that's the principle of אין איסור
חל על איסור. We don't even need, you know, a specific, but
that language is exactly parallel to אין שבועה חלה על שבועה. ein
shevua chala al shevua חל or חלה? chala? It should be חלה.
chala.
Okay. So that תוספות Tosafos, argues, everybody could agree is
doesn't take effect, even רבי יהודה בן בתירה. Rabbi Yehuda Ben Beseira.
And that's the principle of like, you know, of
מושבע ועומד. mushba ve'omeid Okay. But what about if the question is
not that, but the question is, here's my nice סוכה, sukkah. okay,
and here would be the decorations just so you know it's a
סוכה. sukkah, Okay, anyway, so now in this case, the תורה Torah.
says, here's the תורה. Torah
Okay, I guess I could draw הר סיני Har Sinai too. Anyway,
it says sit in a סוכה. sukkah, All right? So that's not
אין איסור חל על איסור. That's a מצוה mitzvah to do something,
right? Ach, god damn, I used your eraser. Okay, that's a מצוה
mitzvah to do something. Okay, and then I say here,
שבועה shevuah
I'll sit in the סוכה. sukkah
So in that case, in that case, that's not אין איסור חל
על איסור. Okay, now maybe it's אין שבועה shevuah. חלה על שבועה
shevuah מושבע ועומד, mushba ve'omeid but maybe not. Maybe all of these
was a classic idea that something cannot become doubly forbidden if it
already has a forbidden state. This is not a question of doubly
forbidden. This is a question of doubly obligated. Okay? So the way
תוספות Tosafot reads it, רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda Ben Beseira
says, yeah, this doesn't take effect. That's your normal principle of איסור
חל על איסור. This takes effect. Why not be doubly obligated to
do something? Okay. And the רבנן Rabbanan say back, no, because since
it's אי אפשר בלאו והן, ee efshar belo vehein, maybe you're right.
In principle you could. These ideas don't apply. But since it can't
be reversed, שבועה shevuah I won't sit in the סוכה, sukkah. right,
that's why in this case you would be exempt from a קרבן.
korban. Okay. Now maybe they're just saying that לשיטתך, leshitatecha, according to
you, רבי יהודה בן בתירה, Rabbi Yehuda Ben Beseira, that you think
מושבע ועומד mushba veomed is more of a reason to be חייב,
chayav. why not concede to the point that you can't say this
in the negative? But you know, maybe אין שבועה shevuah. חלה על
שבועה shevuah might not be relevant, but maybe מושבע ועומד mushba veomed
is. Maybe the רבנן Rabbanan actually say, no, you can't, the same
way you can't be doubly, an object can't be doubly forbidden, you
can't be doubly obligated. That is part of the principle of אין
שבועה shevuah חלה על שבועה. shevuah But it is interesting to realize
that there are two conceptually very distinct places. Yes. So all these
examples are
מצות דאורייתא, mitzvot d'oraisa, both positive and negative. Right. So there's two
other, מצות דרבנן. mitzvot d'rabbanan. What about a universally accepted מנהג? minhag?
Right. No, so there it would take effect. And that's why תוספות
Tosfos even said it would take effect on top of, for example,
the prohibition of חצי שיעור. chatzi shiur. It would take effect possibly
on top of a, there's a discussion, would it take effect on
top of a מצות עשה? mitzvath asei? So תוספות Tosfos has a
whole discussion, which we've mentioned in the past, which is how weighty
the first obligation has to be to prevent the שבועה shevuah from
taking effect on top of it. Okay, let's take a look now
back to גמרא. Gemara תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. יכול נשבע לבטל את
המצוה ולא ביטל יהא חייב. Yachol nishba levatel es hamitzvah velo biteil
yehei chayav. Maybe such a שבועה shevuah should be a binding שבועה,
shevuah and therefore if you didn't do it, you would be obligated
in, you know, even if a שבועה shevuah to negate a מצוה,
mitzvah and you'd be obligated to bring a קרבן. korban Now it's
not being discussed is, again, okay, fine, you obviously it doesn't take
effect and you don't have to fulfill it because you know, the
תורה's Torah not going to recognize a שבועה shevuah to contravene a
מצוה. mitzvah But like if you did it במזיד, bemazeid, would you
bring a קרבן, korban. would you get lashes for שבועת שוא shevuat
shav or something? That's not being discussed. We're totally within the קרבן
korban discussion. Anyway, so maybe it would be a really take effect?
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, להרע או להיטיב, lehara o lehaitiv, to do
bad or to do good. מה הטבה רשות, Mah hatava reshus, the
same way doing good and doing good and doing bad are, the
פשט pshat here is understood to be from the גמרא's Gemara perspective,
like to your body, okay, which basically means doing good would be
to eat something, doing bad would be let's say to go on
a fast or something. Okay, you know? So therefore, מה הטבה רשות,
mah hatava reshus, the same way doing good is means in a
neutral field, right, אף הרעה
רשות. af hara reshus. So that, so then we're talking about doing
bad in a area that's neutral, not doing bad in the world
of מצות. mitzvot. Okay, because not doing a מצוה mitzvah would be
doing bad in the world of מצות. mitzvot. So הוציא נשבע לבטל
את המצוה, hotzi nishba levatel es hamitzvah, so therefore I will exclude
the case of taking an oath to negate a מצוה, mitzvah ולא
ביטל שיהא פטור, velo biteil sheyehei patur, in that case you're exempt,
okay, because we know that the idea of doing good means doing
good in a neutral field. And how do we know that? So
let's keep on reading.
Maybe if you swore to fulfill a מצוה mitzvah and you didn't
you would be חייב. chayav This is again the principle of, right,
מושבע ועומד mushba veomed and so on. So interestingly this ברייתא braisa
doesn't say, oh, you can't be חייב chayav if you took an
oath to be מקיים mekayem because of מושבע ועומד mushba veomed or
whatever, אין שבועה shevuah חלה על שבועה. shevuah Maybe maybe those aren't
relevant principles, maybe it's just figuring out those principles. Okay, so how
do I know a שבועה shevuah to be מקיים mekayem a מצוה
mitzvah is not binding? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar להרע או
להיטיב. lehara o leheitiv. מה הרע רשות, Mah hara reshus, the same
way doing bad means in a discretionary field, in a neutral field,
not in a מצוה mitzvah field, as we just demonstrated above, אף
הטוב רשות. af hatov reshus. So doing good means doing good in
a neutral field, not in the מצוה mitzvah realm. Doing good in
a מצוה mitzvah realm is a שבועה shvua to be מקיים, mekayem,
to sit in a סוכה, sukkah but we're not talking about good
and good and bad in a in a מצוה mitzvah realm, we're
talking about them in a in a neutral realm. אף הטוב רשות,
Af hatov reshus, אוציא נשבע לקיים את המצוה ולא קיים שפטור. otzi
nishba lekayem es hamitzvah velo kiyem shepatur. So a שבועה shvua about
doing good in a מצוה mitzvah realm to do a מצוה mitzvah
is not binding. Now, of course, this is what we call a
not a syllogism, a tautology, or I don't know if it's called
a tautology, but whatever it is, it's circular. Okay, we learned out
that doing bad can't mean to negate a מצוה mitzvah. because doing
good obviously means doing good in a neutral realm, not a מצוה
mitzvah realm. Then we learned out that doing good can't mean to
be מקיים mekayem a מצוה mitzvah, because doing bad obviously means in
a neutral realm and not a מצוה mitzvah. realm. The obvious question
is maybe both of them mean in a מצוה mitzvah realm. How
did you start with one and then you read your own assumptions
and then took them back out again? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
will ask that question. Now, יכול נשבע להרע לעצמו ולא הרע יכול
יהא פטור? yachol nishba lehara le'atzmo velo hara yachol yehei patur? Let's
say you took an oath to do injury to yourself, maybe you
would be exempt? Okay, maybe it would not be binding? תלמוד לומר
Talmud lomar להרע או להיטיב. lehara o leheitiv. מה הטוב רשות אף
הרע רשות. Mah hatov reshus af hara reshus. So again, we're talking
about something that is neutral,
and therefore אוציא נשבע להרע לעצמו ולא הרע שהרשות בידו, otzi nishba
lehara le'atzmo velo hara shehareshus beyado, you're actually allowed to do bad
to yourself. Now what type of bad to yourself are you talking?
So if you take a look at and why are we bothering
saying this? Obviously if it says להרע, lehara, like what else does
it mean? I mean, more obviously means you're doing bad to yourself
than bad to other people, right? Bad to other people you're not
allowed to do. So this if you take a look at תוספות,
Tosfos להרע או להיטיב, lehara o leheitiv, okay, I'm sorry, אוציא נשבע
להרע לעצמו, otzi nishba lehara le'atzmo, that little תוספות, Tosfos כולי האי
בה ולא צריכא אלא לאשמעינן דאדם רשאי לחבול בעצמו. kulei hai bah
velo tzericha ela le'ashmeinan de'adam rashai lachavel be'atzmo. So this is a
very interesting debate, the גמרא gemara doesn't get into it here, but
in בבא קמא Bava Kamma gets into interesting questions about is self-injury
permissible? Right, if I want to go ahead and whatever, I get
pleasure from, I mean, there's sadly some people that they have the
whole issue of with cutting, I don't know if people have heard
of this, like you cut yourself as a way whatever, but for
some reason, anyway, a person wants to go ahead and do things
that are going to be not actually suicide, God forbid, but that
actually does get discussed in the context of that. But things that
cause self-injury, there's a prohibition to be to injure others,
is there a prohibition to do self-injury? So this ברייתא braisa here
is quoted on the side that self-injury is permissible. We just got
through saying that להרע או להיטיב lehara o leheitiv cannot be לבטל
את המצוה levatel es hamitzvah or לקיים את המצוה. lekayem es hamitzvah.
So if you're allowed to do bad to yourself, that must mean
that you can do bad to yourself without violating any הלכה, halacha,
which must mean that self-injury is permissible. Okay, so that's at least
the way that that is learned in the גמרא בבא קמא. Gemara
Bava Kamma. Now you could have said that that just means self-injury
like doing bad to yourself like in a less drastic way, that
you're going to fast for a day, not in a way that's
actually injurious, right, you want to really see a movie but but
you're taking an oath not to go see a movie. Okay, you
could have said it in something, something that is against your interests
but is not physical injury. Alright, so it's not explicit in this
ברייתא, braisa, but it's important to know that the גמרא gemara brings
this in in the discussion in בבא קמא Bava Kamma around that
question of self-injury.
Okay, so that's to that point. Now now we just continue with
what we already sort of knew. Now יכול נשבע להרע לאחרים ולא
הרע שיהא חייב? yachol nishba lehara le'acherim velo hara sheyehei chayav? Maybe
if you took an oath to do bad to others and you
didn't do bad you would be חייב. chayav. Now again, bad here,
like bad could mean like next time Michael comes and asks me
to borrow my lawnmower, I'm not going to give it to him.
That actually would be a binding שבועה, shvua okay, but there's but
in the context of the bad that I have just told you
is implicit in the context of physical injury,
then a שבועה shvua, to do active bad in that way of
actually injury, you know, Michael or whatever, that would actually be נשבע
לבטל את המצוה nishba levatel es hamitzvah or maybe לקיים את העבירה
lekayem es ha'aveirah maybe.
Right, exactly. Well, the מצוה mitzvah is not to injure other people,
meaning מצוה mitzvah doesn't have to be a מצוה קיומית, mitzvah kiyumis,
right, it could be includes a לא תעשה, lo sa'aseh, right? So
that's what we were discussing here, that we're talking both about עשה's
aseh and
לא תעשה's. lo sa'aseh Okay, so
okay, שיהא חייב תלמוד לומר להרע או להיטיב מה הטוב רשות אף
הרע רשות. sheyehei chayav Talmud lomar lehara o leheitiv mah hatov reshus
af hara reshus. אוציא נשבע להרע לאחרים ולא הרע. otzi nishba lehara
le'acherim velo hara. I'm not permitted to do bad to others, so
if I take a שבועה shvua to do bad to others, it's
not binding. But again, the important question is what's included in bad?
Okay. Next time Michael comes and says hi to me I'm going
to ignore him. Alright, you know? So there's things—now, it would be—what
would really be fascinating is, is let's say some of those activities
were because I'm angry at him and I'm getting back at him,
and then it's אסור asur because of לא תקום, lo tikom, not
to take revenge, right? So... but anyway, there certainly are types of
ways that you can be not friendly and bad to other people,
you know, and not gracious or whatever, without being עובר over on
any עבירה. aveirah. Alright, so we're talking about a certain type of
bad that actually would be an עבירה. aveirah. Okay, and that type
of a thing you would not be חייב chayav, for in your
שבועה. shvua
Okay, now it goes on.
Okay, מניין לרבות הטבת אחרים תלמוד לומר או להיטיב. minayin lerabot hatavat
acherim talmud lomar o lehetiv. How do you know that if I
take a שבועה shvua to do good to somebody that I am—that
the שבועה shvua is binding? Because it says או להיטיב. o lehetiv.
Now, ואיזו היא הרעת אחרים—now, veeizo hi haraat acherim now the ברייתא—oh,
braita I'm sorry, I misspoke earlier. The ברייתא braita actually is explicit
that we're talking about real self-inj—real injury, and that's why it's not
binding vis-a-vis other people. Okay. ואיזו היא הרעת אחרים—what veeizo hi haraat
acherim is a הרעת אחרים haraat acherim that would not be binding
about? אכה פלוני, akeh ploni, I'm going to hit so-and-so, ואפצע מוחו,
veeftza mocho, I'm going to bash his head in. Okay. So therefore—oh,
so I—so I forgot, I—I misspoke earlier. It's explicit. So that's why
this ברייתא braita becomes a pretty good evidence that you're allowed to
do self-injury, because הרעת אחרים haraat acherim doesn't take effect, but הרעת
עצמו haraat atzmo does. If you say I'm going to beat myself
up—I hope אפצע מוחו eftza mocho does not mean kill myself. Right,
that's a different story. Okay, but—but—but that's why it's quite clear that
injury of other people is forbidden, and that's why that is a
clear ביטול מצווה. bitul mitzvah. There's ways you could do bad to
others without—without it being a negation of a מצווה. mitzvah. But this
type of bad to others is clearly negation to a מצווה, mitzvah,
it's not binding, the שבועה. shvua But to do it to yourself,
interestingly, is binding, because actually—and that's why this ברייתא braita is evidence—according
to this ברייתא—it's braita not the way we rule—but according to this
ברייתא, braita, you are actually allowed to do self-injury. Which is why—why
does it not rule against—as the other ברייתא? braita? Yeah, the גמרא
gemara brings evidence over there in בבא קמא Bava Kama in the
opposite direction. רמב"ם, Rambam, whatever, the general ruling is the opposite direction.
Right, because even—they say—plastic surgery and stuff. Exactly. That's why those things
are discussions, right? Can you do certain—right, exactly. So self-injury, just so
that it's clear, the—the ruling is—I mean, you have to define what
constitutes injury. If you're doing certain things ultimately for a positive purpose—right,
famous תשובה teshuva about רב משה, Rav Moshe, can you do plastic
surgery purely for not—like when it's reparative—but purely like to improve your
looks? Is that considered to be—like, you know, what constitutes something that
makes it considered to be—yes, you're cutting into your body but ultimately
it's to do something good, not to—you know? So what defines an
act of injury? But the basic ruling is that even self-injury is
forbidden, against this ברייתא. braita. But this ברייתא braita assumes that self-injury—it's
very clear at the end we're talking about physical injury—is permitted. Now,
the question is, why does it take effect if I say that
I'm going to do good to Michael? If we just said that
when I said I'm going to do bad to Michael, it doesn't
take effect because it's לבטל את המצווה. levatel et hamitzvah.
So why does it take effect when I say I'm going to
do good to Michael? Isn't it a problem of הן בלא לאו?
hen belo lav? That you can't reverse it? So the point is,
is that there's a whole middle ground between good and bad. Meaning
if the שבועה shvua was—I'm going to—there's a—I was going to take
a שבועה shvua that I'm not going to bash Michael's head in.
So actually that שבועה shvua wouldn't be binding. You know why? Because
I can't say it in the negative. The negative—or the opposite—the opposite
is I will bash his head in. So interestingly, the שבועה shvua
to do nothing bad is actually not binding because I can't say
it in the reverse, right? So
if I say—but—if I take a שבועה shvua that I will, I
don't know, give Michael צדקה, tzedakah, if I take a שבועה shvua
that I'm going to go ahead and help Michael mow his lawn,
okay, that is
הן בלא לאו. hen belo lav. Because when you negate that—you won't—you
could do—well, okay, true. But when you negate that, you just get
into—well, the neutral zone. I'm not going to give him money. I'm
not going to mow his lawn. That's okay, right? I don't have
to do you a favor. So it's interesting, right? The שבועה shvua
to do good works, even though a שבועה shvua to do bad—you
know, in a serious type of bad—doesn't work. A שבועה shvua to
do good works because you can reverse it and get into the
absence of good. You can get into the neutral zone. The absence
of it doesn't bring you into—it's good and not bad. It's not
bad. However, interestingly, a שבועה shevua to not hurt somebody doesn't work
because the opposite of not hurting is hurting, and that actually you're
not allowed to do. Okay, so you got those sort of three
zones? Right?
Here's
good—it's like my kids do D&D, I don't know if anybody knows,
right? The alignment: good, neutral, bad—evil or something. Okay, and—so you've got
the good, the bad, and the neutral. Yeah,
exactly. So the neutral is, I'm—I won't hurt Michael. Okay. That שבועה
shevua doesn't take effect. Because the negative of that is will hurt.
So since I can't take a שבועה shevua that I will hurt,
the שבועה shevua of won't hurt doesn't take effect. Wait, on yourself
you can? Yeah, yeah, we're talking about you, okay? Do it to
somebody else. But if the good is I will help,
okay? So this שבועה shevua doesn't take effect because this one doesn't
take effect. But will help does take effect because the opposite of
will help is won't help. Okay? And therefore I can, so won't
help, you know, since won't help is something I could say, will
help is something that I can say. Yes. So this isn't exactly
parallel. A parallel case in the good side would be I will
unload your donkey. Okay? No, or on the other side a parallel
case would be I won't like avoid saying hello to you because
if I did מתקיים mekayeim it, I would be not saying hello,
which is not an איסור. Right, right. We already established that this
doesn't work because it's לבטלה levatala of a מצוה. mitzvah. The question
we're asking is: Do these work when they're not in directly מצוה
mitzvah thing? When they're in the neutral realm? Like on both sides,
would it work if it's not לבטלה? levatala? Right. Is doing bad
when it's not negating a מצוה, mitzvah like I'm not going to
lend Michael my lawnmower or whatever, you know, or I'm going to
sneer at him when I see him next time, like something that's
not just an absence of a favor. Right. So that's true too.
But in like, so you're right, there are configurations where all of
these work as long as they don't conflict with a מצוה. mitzvah.
But assuming that we're starting here and like something that you're not
allowed to do, ironically if you just say you won't do bad,
it's not a שבועה, shevua because the opposite of not doing bad
is doing bad. Okay? Whereas if you say you will do good,
that is, okay, Jacob is correct. If will do good means a
מצוה mitzvah that you're obligated to do, then it won't take effect
for that reason. But if you say you'll do good in a
way where you have some discretion, right? So I'm going to give
Michael my צדקה tzedakah rather than giving it to somebody else or
something of that nature, right, it does take effect because the opposite
of that is the absence of doing it. It's not the doing
of something bad. Okay, so now let's take a look.
Okay.
Now okay. Now the גמרא gemara, says like this: וממאי דקרא. umimai
de'kra. Now we're going to get back to this idea of how
we knew to exclude דבר מצוה. dvar mitzvah. Because we excluded דבר
מצוה dvar mitzvah because we said, oh, הטבה hatavah has to be
like הרעה, haraah, right? What?
Yeah, yeah, דרבנן. derabbanan. Yeah, yeah, בסוכות besukkot if you do the
lawnmower you would.
Yeah, correct. Okay now we said all of this, we know to
exclude דבר מצוה dvar mitzvah because we say, well, if doing bad
is
in a רשות reshut area, so doing good is that, and if
doing good is that, then doing bad is that. So we sort
of just we're totally circular.
So the גמרא Gemara is going to say: How did you know
to read bad and good and read them off each other being
about רשות? reshut? Maybe they're both talking about the מצוה mitzvah realm.
Maybe the קרא kray is exactly saying if you took an oath
להרע lehara to negate a מצוה mitzvah or להיטיב lehayotiv or to
do a מצוה. mitzvah And maybe exactly that, like you know, let's
just assume we're talking about מצות. mitzvot. Why do we assume we're
talking about רשות? reshut? The whole argument was circular. So that's what
the גמרא Gemara, says.
וממאי, umimai, says the גמרא, Gemara how do we know דקרא דבמילי
דרשות כתיבי? de'kra d'b'meilei d'reshut ktivi? That the whole פסוק pasuk is
written in רשות, reshut, which is sort of you know how you
learned out all your הלכות. halachot. דילמא בדבר מצוה כתיבי? dilma bidvar
mitzvah ktivi? Maybe the whole case is talking about מצוה mitzvah cases,
right? And להרע ולהיטיב lehara u'lehayotiv means to negate a מצוה mitzvah,
or to fulfill a מצוה. mitzvah Okay, לא סלקא דעתך. lo salka
datach. No, that doesn't make sense.
דבעינן הטבה דומיא דהרעה והרעה דומיא דהטבה. de'beinan hatavah dumya de'haraah v'haraah
dumya de'hatavah. Okay because they both have to be similar, דאקיש הרעה
להטבה. d'akish haraah l'hatavah. Now why would that not work? Let's assume
that the פסוקים psukim we're talking, the way רש"י Rashi reads this,
only in the מצוה mitzvah realm. Okay תוספות Tosfos says maybe it's
even in the מצוה mitzvah realm, but anyway let's just go with
רש"י. Rashi. Let's assume the פסוקים psukim we're talking specifically in the
מצוה mitzvah? realm. Here's the problem we would have. Here's why: Because
since הטבה hatavah good has to be like bad and bad has
to be like good, so it says like this: מה הטבה אינה
בביטול מצוה אף הרעה אינה בביטול מצוה. mah hatavah einah b'bitul mitzvah
af haraah einah b'bitul mitzvah. So דאקיש הרעה להטבה, d'akish haraah l'hatavah,
so the same way, so we would start by saying okay they're
מצוה mitzvah. realm. So a שבועה להיטיב shvua lehayotiv is something that
is not going to negate a מצוה mitzvah but would fulfill a
מצוה, mitzvah right? A שבועה להיטיב shvua lehayotiv for example רש"י Rashi
said would be I'll eat מצה matzah on סדר seder night. So
אף הרעה, af haraah, so a שבועה shevua of doing bad could
not be negating a מצוה mitzvah because it has to be like
הטבה. hatavah. So it has to be something אינה בביטול מצוה. einah
b'bitul mitzvah. So then what would be an example of doing bad
in a מצוה mitzvah realm that would not be negating a מצוה
mitzvah, but would be fulfilling a מצוה? mitzvah. So here it gets
a little confusing. רש"י Rashi said we would have to interpret the
bad part to be bad in terms of your bodily pleasures but
not bad in terms of a מצוה. mitzvah. So the bad that
could be a fulfillment of a מצוה mitzvah? is you let's say
take a שבועה shevua not to eat חמץ chametz on פסח. Pesach.
רש"י Rashi makes it very nice and convenient that we can talk
about eating מצה. matzah. Are we there already? Yeah, yeah, but the
whole point is maybe we should learn the opposite of that from
this. Okay? So that the whole thing is the סדר seder night
or whatever. But the whole point is maybe we should learn the
opposite of that. Okay, so the whole thing is the סדר Seder
night or whatever, so that or פסח Pesach that there's a positive,
there's a good, which is eating, which is bodily good and מצוה
mitzvah good, and then there's a not eating חמץ, chametz, which is
a bodily bad but a מצוה mitzvah good. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara is sort of saying like this: because of the link of
good and bad, I would have had to say that even the
bad just means a bodily bad but a מצוה mitzvah good. And
that they—it would be talking about eating, like the good would be
eating מצה matzah and the bad would be not eating חמץ. chametz.
Okay, but if that's true, says the גמרא, Gemara so הרע גופא
טובה היא, hara gufa tova hi, then it's not really conceptually bad,
because it really is good. It really is, again, if our
primary measuring stick is מצוה, mitzvah, then those are just
two שבועות לקיים את המצוה. shvuos lekayem es hamitzvah. So and then
I'd have the same problem in the opposite way. והקיש הטבה להרע
מה הרע אינו בקיום מצוה אף הטבה אינו בקיום מצוה. vehakeish hatava
lehara mah hara eino b’kiyum mitzvah af hatava eino b’kiyum mitzvah. I
would say the opposite, I would say: okay, let's say I start
in the other direction. הרע hara would be a way that would
be negating a מצוה. mitzvah, You take a שבועה shevua that you
won't eat מצה matzah on סדר Seder night. So הטבה hatava would
have to be a way of negating a מצוה. mitzvah, How would
הטבה hatava be negating a מצוה? mitzvah, Well, if you could do
bodily pleasure and negate a מצוה mitzvah, would be: you will eat
חמץ. chametz. Okay, but if that's what you're saying, then it just
becomes another version of bad in the מצוה mitzvah, realm. הטבה גופא
רעה היא. hatava gufa ra’a hi. Now, so that's all very complicated
because what the גמרא Gemara basically said is, it said: I would
insist that the הטבה, hatava, if it's talking in the מצוה mitzvah
realm, be good in terms of a מצוה, mitzvah so I'd insist
that the הרע hara be good in terms of a מצוה, mitzvah.
but then it would be redundant. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says
if that's your logic, that you say it can't be talking about
מצוה, mitzvah because if it's talking about מצוה, mitzvah, I would say,
well the הטבה hatava has to be a good מצוה, mitzvah so
the הרע hara has to be a good מצוה, mitzvah right? And
then it becomes redundant, and vice versa. So the גמרא Gemara says
you could say the same if we're talking in the neutral realm.
Okay? That if they really have to be so similar, it's again,
you're just making your problems for yourself. You're insisting that they be
really similar. If they're really similar, then you say, oh well, then
it can't be because it's redundant, right? So the גמרא Gemara says
you would have the same problem if you're dealing in the non-מצוה
mitzvah realm. So the גמרא Gemara says: אי הכי בדבר
הרשות נמי לא משכחת לה. ee hachi bidvar hareshus nami lo meshakchas
lah. Okay? Because you would say: oh, הטבה hatava means I'm going
to eat. Well, הרע, hara, it can't mean I'm not going to
eat, because it has to be like הטבה. hatava. So הרע hara
must mean something else—I'm not going to eat bad food. Okay, well,
that's just like הטבה, hatava, right? So if you insist that the
הרע hara be like הטבה hatava and achieve the same goal, you
can't then turn around and say, oh, but now it's redundant, so
obviously it's not true. You could say that in the מצוה realm
and you could say that in the רשות reshus realm. So anyway,
you still have not really explained what entitles you to read the
פסוקים psukim to be talking about רשות reshus and not talking about
מצוה. Okay, אלא, ela, fine. מדאיצטריך או לרבות הטבת אחרים שמע מינה
בדבר הרשות כתיבי. mide’itztarich o l’rabos hatavas acheirim shma mina bidvar hareshus
ksivi. Okay, so here's why. Forget the whole thing what the ברייתא
braisa said. You're right, you really can't learn it from that, that
was really totally circular. The way we learn out we're not talking
about מצוות mitzvot, is from a different point. When it says להרע
או להיטיב, lehara o lehaitiv, so the או o tells me that
it would include doing nice things to Michael. Okay? Now, why do
you need a פסוק pasuk to tell me a שבועה shevua to
do nice to Michael is binding? Of course it would be. Why
wouldn't it be? Here's why. דאי סלקא דעתך בדבר מצוה כתיבי השתא
הרעת אחרים איתשרי הטבת אחרים מיבעיא. de’ee salka dach’tach bidvar mitzvah ksivi
hashta haras acheirim itshri hatavas acheirim mibaya. Says: if
להרע או להיטיב lehara o lehaitiv means that I can take a
שבועה shevua לקיים את המצוה ולבטל את המצוה, lekayem es hamitzvah u’levatel
es hamitzvah, so it would—I would also, right? Assuming that the פסוקים
psukim were to be talking about מצוה להרע או להיטיב, lehara o
lehaitiv, it would mean that I could take a שבועה shevua to
go ahead and beat up Michael, even though it would be לבטל
את המצוה. levatel es hamitzvah. Okay? That's what I would learn from
להרע או להיטיב. lehara o lehaitiv. Once I knew that, would I
need a פסוק pasuk to tell me that I could take a
מצוה, a שבועה shevua to do something nice to Michael? Of course
not. If I can take a שבועה shevua to do something injurious
to him, of course I could take a שבועה shevua to do
something nice to him. So why do I need a פסוק pasuk
to tell me I can take a שבועה shevua to do something
nice to Michael? The only logic is that we've already established I
cannot take a שבועה לבטל את המצוה. shvua levatel es hamitzvah. So
we've already established that I can't take a שבועה shevua to beat
up Michael. So I might have thought based on the principle of
לאו והן, lav vehein that I also can't take a שבועה shevua
to do something nice to Michael. Maybe that would be seen as
not reversible. Maybe I would have thought that the reversible of being
nice is beating him up. Okay? So because I needed a פסוק
pasuk to tell me I can take a שבועה shevua to do
something nice to somebody else, it makes it clear, it's implicit that
I can't take a שבועה shevua. to beat up somebody else. And
that must be because there's already a principle that you can't take
a שבועה לבטל את המצוה. shvua levatel es hamitzvah. So as opposed
to everything the whole ברייתא braisa said, that the way I know
we're not talking about a מצוה is הטבה דומיא דהרע והרע דומיא
דהטבה, hatava dumya dehara vehara dumya dehatava, the גמרא Gemara basically says:
nah, that's not where you learn it from. That's all circular. You
just read your assumption in. The way you know that you can't
take a שבועה לבטל את המצוה shvua levatel es hamitzvah is because...
you need a פסוק pasuk to tell me that you can do
something nice to somebody else, which shows that we're already assuming that
you can't take the שבועה shevua. to do something injurious to somebody
else. Okay? אי סלקא דעתך בדבר מצוה כתיבי, Ee salka dachach bidvar
mitzvah ketivi, had the verse told me that I could do מצוה
good and bad, meaning take a שבועה לבטל את המצוה, shevua levatel
et hamitzvah, השתא הרעה לכם איצטריכי סופא, Hashta hara'ah lachem itztreichi sofa,
if I'd be able to do something a שבועה shevua would be
binding to do something injurious to somebody else, הטבה לכם מבעיא? Hatavah
lachem mibaya? So that's why I know from that או o that
tells me I can be a שבועה shevua to do nice, that's
where I learn that I can't take a שבועה לבטל את המצוה.
shevua levatel et hamitzvah. So the גמרא Gemara says, והאי או מבעיא
ליה לחלק. vehai o mibaya leh lechalek. Wait one minute. No, no.
So now fine, I get fine, you've established your point. That's where
you learn you can't take a שבועה לבטל את המצוה. shevua levatel
et hamitzvah. But now let's talk about the דרשה drasha itself. עולא
מותיב, Ulla motive, that extra או o told you you could take
a שבועה shvuo to do nice to somebody else. But how do
you say that extra או o is extra? You need the extra
או o to tell me A or B, not A and B.
If it had said להרע ולהטיב, lehara u'leheitiv, you would have thought
that a שבועה shvuo is only binding if it has both elements,
both good and bad. Okay? והאי או מבעיא ליה לחלק, vehai o
mibaya leh lechalek, you need it, it's not extra, you need it
to distinguish between one שבועה shvuo of doing good, one שבועה shvuo
of doing bad. If it had just been a ו, vav, you
would have said you needed both components. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לחלק לא צריך קרא. Lechalek lo tzarich kra. No, a ו, vav,
even a ו vav would have been read as an or, would
not have been read as an and. So the גמרא gemara says,
הניחא לרבי יוחנן, Haniicha le'Rabbi Yochanan, that's true לרבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
we'll see in a minute, says that a ו vav can be
normally would be read as an or. אלא לרבי יאשיה מאי איכא
למימר, Ela le'Rabbi Yoshiya mai ika lemeimar, רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya says
a ו vav would be read as an and and you needed
an או o to make it into an or. דתניא, detanya, we
taught a ברייתא: baraita: איש
אשר יקלל את אביו ואת אמו, Ish asher yekalel et aviv ve'et
imo, okay, a man who curses his mother and father, right, is
deserving of the death penalty. דמיו בו אביו ואמו קלל דמיו בו.
Damav bo aviv imo kilel damav bo. Okay, so אין לי אלא
אביו ואמו, ein li ela aviv ve'imo, I only know if he
curses them both at together. אביו ולא אמו אמו ולא אביו מנין,
Aviv velo imo imo velo aviv minayin, how do I know one
without the other? תלמוד לומר אביו ואמו קלל. Talmud lomar aviv imo
kilel. The first verse begins אשר יקלל את אביו ואת אמו, asher
yekalel et aviv ve'et imo, so the word קלל kilel appears next
to the word אביו. aviv. The end of the verse says אביו
ואמו קלל. Aviv imo kilel. The word קלל kilel appears next to
the word אמו. imo. So we're saying קלל kilel with אביו aviv
alone and קלל kilel with אמו imo alone. אביו קלל אמו קלל,
Aviv kilel imo kilel, דברי רבי יאשיה. divrei Rabbi Yoshiya. So רבי
יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya said the normal ו, vav, I would have read
that to mean together and I needed to learn from a verse
it means apart, one or the other. רבי יונתן אומר, Rabbi Yonatan
omer, משמע שניהם כאחד ומשמע אחד בפני עצמו. mashma shneihem ke'echad umashma
echad bifnei atzmo. No, I would read the verse to include, to
refer to both cases, together and apart. So ו vav is, you
know, both possibilities are or both reads are correct. So yes, if
you curse them both you're חייב chayav and if you curse one
of them you're
חייב. chayav עד שיפרט לך הכתוב יחדיו, ad sheyafrit lecha hakatuv yachdav,
like it says לא תחרוש בשור ובחמור יחדיו, lo tachrosh beshor uvachamor
yachdav, don't do it together. יחדיו yachdav makes it clear. Without that
explicit, I read it as an or. So the גמרא gemara says,
so okay, so for the argument that a ו vav would have
meant or, the word או o is extra and that tells me
to include doing good to other people. Okay? But if the word
if I need an או o to divide, then how is that
או o extra? So the גמרא gemara says, אפילו תימא רבי יאשיה,
afillu teima Rabbi Yoshiya, fine, here's how it would work according to
רבי יאשיה. Rabbi Yoshiya. The או o wouldn't be extra. So where
would I learn this idea to exclude a לבטל את המצוה? levatel
et hamitzvah? Right? Because now we're saying או o teaches me a
שבועה shvuo works to do good to other people and therefore implicitly
I learn from there that a שבועה shvuo doesn't work לבטל את
המצוה. levatel et hamitzvah. But if I don't have the או o
to tell me that, where do I learn this principle of a
שבועה לבטל את המצוה shevua levatel et hamitzvah doesn't work? So it
says סבירא ליה כרבי עקיבא דדריש ריבוי ומיעוט. savra leh ke'Rabbi Akiva
dedarish ribui umi'ut. Okay? So remember רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said, you
know, להרע או להיטיב לכל אשר יבטא, lehara o leheitiv lechol asher
yevata, that everything is included, ריבוי ומיעוט. ribui umi'ut. The only one
thing is excluded. The פרט prat or whatever, the מיעוט mi'ut of
להרע או להיטיב lehara o leheitiv excludes only one thing. So if
I asked you what is the one thing that would be on
the top of your list that the תורה Torah should exclude from
a שבועה shvuo being binding, you would say maybe you wouldn't say
but the rabbis would say a שבועה shvuo, to negate what the
תורה Torah obligates you to do. So that's where I learn that
we're not talking about the realm of מצוות, okay? אי אמרת בשלמא
דבר הרשות כתיב, Ee amrat bishlama dvar hareshut ketiv, if you're basically
the שבועה shvuo world is a world of דבר הרשות, dvar hareshut,
so ממילא דבר מצוה, mimela dvar mitzvah, that opens up the idea
or, you know, that means that the one thing that could be
excluded would be לבטל מצוה. levatel mitzvah. אלא אי אמרת בדבר מצוה
כתיבי מאי קמימעיט? Ela ee amrat bidvar mitzvah ketivi mai kamime'it? But
if the
תורה להרע או להיטיב Torah lehara o leheitiv means לקיים מצוה או
לבטל מצוה, lekayem mitzvah o levatel mitzvah, right, oh my God, if
I can take an oath from the two extremes to do something
that God wants me to do and I can take an oath
to go against something God wants me to do, so everything in
the middle will also include, right? So what would be excluded? So
it must mean that no, the פסוקים psukim are talking about דבר
הרשות. dvar hareshut. The only the one thing that clearly we you
would not be work for would be לבטל את המצוה. levatel et
hamitzvah. Once I learn that לבטל את המצוה levatel et hamitzvah is
excluded, I would also therefore learn that לקיים את המצוה lekayem et
hamitzvah is excluded based on
להרע או להיטיב. lehara o leheitiv. So Rabbi Yehuda Ben Beseira says
look we לקיים המצוה lekayem hamitzvah should be binding and the rabbis
say well and maybe it should be but it's not לאו והן
lav vehein you can't reverse it. So רבנן שפיר קאמרי ליה לרבי
יהודה בן בתירא Rabbanan shapir kaamre lei le-Rabbi Yehuda Ben Beseira they
say they're saying they're making good arguments for Rabbi Yehuda Ben Beseira,
okay, presumably the only thing he could say back is that he
doesn't require לאו והן. lav vehein So let's see what it says.
רבי יהודה בן בתירא אמר לך אטו הטבת אחרים לאו אף על
גב דליתיה בכלל הרעת אחרים ורבי רחמנא Rabbi Yehuda Ben Beteira amar
lach atu hatavas acherim lav af al gav delisayh bichlal haraas acherim
verabi rachmana it says
one minute but you guys just said guys anyway you said that
if you say you're going to do good to somebody that's included
meaning even though you can't reverse that. He says yeah I don't
need לאו והן and I'll prove to you I don't need that
even you don't really need לאו והן because you said you could
take a שבועה to be nice to your friend well you can't
take a שבועה to hurt your
friend, okay. So הכי נמי בקיום מצוה hachi nami bekiyum mitzvah so
also when you take a שבועה to do a מצוה אף על
גב דליתיה בביטול מצוה af al gav delisayh bevittul mitzvah even though
you can't negate it רבי רחמנא rabi rachmana it's included. Yeah sometimes
you don't need לאו והן. I don't know if he says you
always don't need לאו והן or at least in this case you
don't need לאו והן but you guys also admit that there are
exceptions to that rule or maybe the rule doesn't exist. לרבנן leRabbanan
the rabbis would say back התם איתא בלאו הטיב hasam issa belav
hetiv like I said before the opposite of I'll do good to
Michael is not that I'm going to hurt him it's just that
I won't do good to him. So that actually is a binding
שבועה and is not a problematic is not negating anything. הכא מי
איתא בלאו אקיים hacha mi issa belav akayem here the opposite of
I'll sit in the סוכה sukkah. is I won't sit in the
סוכה. I won't sit in the סוכה is ביטול מצוה vittul mitzvah
it's not it's not it's not it doesn't work. Okay, so that's
why basically the גמרא gemara says you know I'm sorry but you
know this can't work now either because אין מושבע ועומד ein mushba
veomed right? It's interesting that's not what's being underscored. Maybe they're saying
לשיטתך leshitascha that מושבע ועומד mushba veomed doesn't matter or maybe this
is only a concept when it's like an איסור but they're saying
minimally because you can't reverse it and say I won't sit in
the סוכה. And presumably רבי יהודה בן בתירא either in general does
not need לאו והן which is what the גמרא gemara sounded like
earlier or at least in this case does not need it. Okay
let's now go to the next משנה. שבועה
שלא אוכל כיכר זו Shevua shelo ochel kikar zo שבועה שלא אוכלנה.
shevua shelo ochlenna. Guy takes a שבועה I won't eat this thing
I won't eat it. Seem like the same word same thing in
different ways. שבועה שלא אוכלנה shevua shelo ochlenna says it a third
time. תוספות Tosfos doesn't have that third time I'll get back to
them in a minute. ואכלה veachalah and he eat it אינו חייב
אלא אחת. eino chayav ela achas. He only gets one. That is
this case. מושבע ועומד right? Except it's not an עבירה aveira it
was אסור assur once because of a שבועה and again because of
a שבועה and again those other things do not take effect. That's
not מושבע ועומד מהר סיני that's מושבע ועומד from your own שבועה.
Okay? ואין שבועה חלה על שבועה. veein shevua chala al shevua. Okay.
אינו חייב
אלא אחת. eino chayav ela achas. זו היא שבועת ביטוי zo hi
shevuas bitui this example this is a classic example of a שבועת
ביטוי shevuas bitui meaning the case in the תורה of the קרבן
korban. שחייבין על זדונה מכות shechayavin al zedona makkos if you willfully
violate it you get lashes ועל שגגתה קרבן עולה ויורד veal shigagasa
korban oleh veyored and if you unintentionally violate it you bring this
קרבן korban. of variable cost. שבועת Shevuas now that's so that's שבועת
ביטוי shevuas bitui that's future oriented
and then you go ahead and you violate it. Past was the
whole debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael.
But everybody agrees that future oriented is where if you do it
willfully violate it you get lashes, unintentionally you bring a קרבן. korban
Past, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael would say you never bring a קרבן
korban. it's only שבועת שקר. shevuas sheker. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would
say it's both שבועת שקר shevuas sheker and שבועת ביטוי shevuas bitui
if you do it I mean those are just two different labels
we attach but it's one שבועה. But anyway that if you in
the past if you're lying about the past willfully you get lashes
שבועת שקר. shevuas sheker. If you're שוגג shogeg about the past that's
the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael.
And now the third category is שבועת שוא חייבין על זדונה מכות
ועל שגגתה פטור. shevuas shav chayavin al zedona makkos veal shigagasa patur.
A שבועה for naught is you get lashes but there's everybody agrees
there's no קרבן. korban. What's a שבועה for naught? The easiest example
is that you swear on something that's patently obvious or patently false,
okay. Somebody swears that two plus two is four or that two
plus two is five, okay that would be a שבועת שוא shevuas
shav everybody would agree no קרבן korban there and you would bring
if it's willful you get you get lashes. Okay let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara because now we get to the אין
שבועה חלה על שבועה idea. Alright. למה
לי למתני שבועה שלא אוכל שבועה שלא אוכלנה. Lama li lemasni shevua
shelo ochel shevua shelo ochlenna. So now why says the גמרא Gemara
we understand why you want to say שבועה שלא אוכל שבועה שלא
אוכל shevua shelo ochel shevua shelo ochel you want to teach me
the principle of אין שבועה חלה על שבועה that there's only one
קרבן. korban But why was the second one phrased as שלא אוכלנה
shelo ochlenna okay how is that different from שלא אוכל כיכר זו?
shelo ochel kikar zo? So גמרא Gemara says הא קמשמע לן טעמא
דאמר שבועה שלא אוכל והדר אמר שבועה שלא אוכלנה ha kamashma lan
taama damar shevua shelo ochel vehadar amar shevua shelo ochlenna that it's
the order mattered why דלא מיחייב אלא חדא delo michayev ela chada
because the first one took effect. But the second one didn't take
effect. אבל אמר שלא אוכלנה והדר אמר שלא אוכל, Aval amar shelo
ochalnah v'hadar amar shelo ochel, but if you first said I won't
eat it and then you said I won't eat this loaf, מחייב
תרתי, mechayev tartei, actually the second one does take effect. Why? It
seems completely redundant. כי דרבא, Ki d'Rava, because Rava says actually the
way you articulate it indicates what the scope of your שבועה is.
דאמר שבועה שלא אוכל כיכר זו, D'amar shvuo shelo ochel kikar zo,
if you say I won't eat this loaf, כיון דאכל מינה כזית
חייב, kivan d'achal minah k'zayis chayav, even if you eat one כזית
k'zayis you transgress, because that he says means I won't eat from
this loaf, okay? And therefore even a כזית k'zayis transgresses. שלא אוכלנה,
Shelo ochalnah, I won't eat it, somehow for him means I won't
eat its entirety. ואינו חייב עד שיאכל את כולה, V'eino chayav ad
she-yochal es kulah, you have to eat its entirety. So therefore if
the guy first took an oath שלא אוכלנה, shelo ochalnah, okay,
like I don't fully get why it has this sort of different
phraseology, but you can understand, right, that's a slightly different
phraseology would suggest you mean I won't eat from it or I
won't eat the whole thing, okay? So therefore what Rava says is
if you were to, so based on Rava, if you were to
first say let's just say you were explicit, you would first say
a שבועה that I won't eat this whole loaf and then I
said a שבועה I won't eat a כזית k'zayis of it, does
the second one take effect? Yes! Because the second one forbids more
than the first one. The second one forbids every כזית, k'zayis, the
first one just forbids a whole loaf. If you first said שבועה
I won't eat a כזית k'zayis and then you say שבועה I
won't eat the whole loaf, the second one doesn't take effect. It's
completely redundant. So that's what the משנה is teaching you,
that אוכלנה ochalnah means the whole loaf, and therefore if it comes
second it doesn't take effect, but if it came first, then the
second one which means כזית k'zayis does take effect. Okay, fine.
Now, שבועה שלא אוכלנה ואכלה אינו חייב אלא אחת. Shvuo shelo ochalnah
v'achalah eino chayav ela achas. Moving on. So that's the first point,
that אוכלנה ochalnah means the whole loaf and order matters. הסו למה
לי? Ha su lama li? Why do I need to say three
שבועות? shvuos? שלא אוכלנה שלא אוכלנה שלא אוכל Shelo ochalnah shelo ochalnah
shelo ochel or whatever. So the גמרא Gemara, says, I'm going to
get back to that, הא קמשמע לן חיובא הוא דליכא השבועה איכא.
Ha kamashma lan chiyuva hu d'leika ha-shvuo ika. The reason to tell
me that the guy, like why bother saying that he took a
third one? So the way רש''י Rashi reads it is, you're right,
that's a completely extra scenario, and it's thrown in to tell you
that something else. What else does it tell me? Now how this
fits into the fact that it describes the scenario this way is
not clear, but it's to tell me that you're not חייב, chayav
הא קמשמע לן חיובא הוא דליכא השבועה איכא. ha kamashma lan chiyuva
hu d'leika ha-shvuo ika. The שבועה is like still hovering. What does
it mean that the שבועה is hovering? Okay, it didn't take effect
because the earlier one was blocking it, okay? But if you somehow
manage to remove the earlier one, this one would actually take effect.
How could you remove the earlier one? Right. דאי משכח רווחא חיילא,
D'ei mashkach revacha chaila, if it finds some space to take effect,
it will take effect. How could it find space? למאי הלכתא לכדרבא.
Le-mai hilchasa le-chi-d'Rava. Again a teaching of Rava. דאמר רבא, D'amar Rava,
שנישאל על הראשונה, shenishal al ha-rishona, you went to a חכם chacham
and you said I have regret for taking this first oath etc.
and you did a היתר נדר hetter neder or היתר שבועה hetter
shvuo on the first oath, okay? But either you didn't have regret
on the second one or you forgot about the second one, and
you only asked about the first one. So you up, now when
a חכם chacham is מתיר matir a נדר neder or שבועה, it's
not only from now going forward. It's retroactively, because of your regret,
it's like you never took it. So if you had never taken
it, now we look backwards in time and we say okay, so
going back two weeks you never took the first one, but you
did take the second one. So now we realize that for the
last two weeks the second שבועה has been in effect, not the
first one, because we reassess the history now based on what we're
just learning, okay? שאם נישאל על הראשונה חלה עליו השניה תחתיה, She-im
nishal al ha-rishona chala alav ha-shniya tachteiha, the second one takes its
place and its effect. Now before we go on to analyze that,
I just want to say that תוספות Tosfos does not have the
third scenario, שלא אוכל שלא אוכלנה shelo ochel shelo ochalnah etc. So
where does תוספות Tosfos learn this from? He said he doesn't have
the גירסא like what's the phrase in Gemara? הסו למה לי. Ha
su lama li. No, תוספות Tosfos says it's about the phrasing. The
phrasing is, this is a very good read of תוספות because it
also explains
where the גמרא Gemara learns that we're talking about this idea that
the other one is hovering. Where did it get that from? From
the extra scenario that he took a third oath? So תוספות says
no, it's from the following phrase: אינו חייב אלא אחת. Eino chayav
ela achas.
Okay, that phrase in the משנה, you took these two oaths, for
תוספות it was only two, you're only חייב for one קרבן. korban
תוספות says that phrase could have been said another way. How else
could you have said you're חייב for one קרבן korban
instead of אינו חייב אלא אחת? eino chayav ela achas?
חייב אחת. Chayav achas. Okay, so תוספות says why do you say
אינו חייב אלא אחת? eino chayav ela achas?
That suggests that there still is the possibility the second, well the
second one is still there. but you're only חייב even though there
were two שבועות shavuos there, you only are bringing one קרבן. This
more sounds like only one exists, the other one we're completely ignoring.
This one sounds like, yeah, it's true, we acknowledge that they're both
there, but you're still only going to bring one קרבן. So this,
from this, we're מדייק medayek that the other one is still seen
as sort of present and hovering and could retroactively take effect if
you retroactively removed the first one. Okay. Very nice דיוק diyuk ר'
תוספות. Reb Tosfos. Okay, now the גמרא goes to discuss whether this
is really true or not. Okay, let's take a look. לימא מסייע
ליה. Leima mesaya lay. Let's see if we can bring support for
רבא. Rava.
מי שנדר ב' נזיריות Mi shenadar beis neziros ומנה ראשונה. umana rishona.
Somebody took two נזירות, neziros, he took a נדר neder אהא בנזיר
אהא בנזיר, ah be-nazir ah be-nazir, okay, and he counted the thirty
days for the first one, והפריש עליה קרבן, vehifrish aleha korban, he
separated a קרבן to end his נזירות. neziros. אחר כך נשאל על
הראשונה. Achar kach nish'al al harishona. Before he got around to bringing
the קרבן and after he... it's like why bother at this stage,
but he went to a חכם chacham and he totally uprooted his
first נזירות. neziros.
Okay. עלתה לו שנייה בראשונה. Alsa lo shniya berishona. Now we retroactively
say, oh, okay, so the last thirty days you've been keeping your
second נזירות, neziros, and the קרבן that you thought you were separating
for your first, you separated for your second, and now go bring
your קרבן and you'll be יוצא yotze your second נזירות. neziros. So
you see that it remains hovering. So that seems like a pretty
good proof for רבא. Rava. Says the גמרא, הכי השתא? hachi hashta?
What type of comparison is that? התם Hosam נזירות neziros
מי איתא. mi isa. Everybody agrees the second נזירות neziros is present.
How do you know? Because guess what the הלכה halacha is? Let's
say he wasn't נשאל nish'al and he accepted two נזירות. neziros. Then
he would do one, he would do the second one after the
first one. דכי מנה לראשונה בעי מיהדר ומימנא לשנייה. De-chi mana lerishona
bai mehader umimna lishniya.
Okay, there, if he hadn't been נשאל, nish'al, after he done the
first, he'd have to do the second. So of course the second
one remains present and hovering. בלא שאלה, Belo sheilah, if he had
not done a שאלה. sheilah. הכא Hacha שבועה שנייה shvuah shniya מי
איתא כלל? mi isa klal? Had he not been שואל shoel on
the first one, there would have been no ramifications of the second
one. So it's so because of that, because it's not without שאלה
sheilah we don't see it as being present, there's no clear ramifications.
So it's not clear that we would go ahead and say that
it's still... it's always seen as present for you know, even with...
even when it didn't take effect. Okay. אמר רבא Amar Rava מי
איתא כלל. mi isa klal. So
fine. So the גמרא says... so he didn't really prove his point.
Okay, but even though he didn't prove it from the נזיר Nazir
case, he still says it's correct. The only reason it didn't take
effect was because of the first one, if we can updo retroactively
undo the first one, the second one will take effect. Now here's
another teaching of רבא, Rava, and we'll just sort of quote it
now and we'll pick up tomorrow. אמר רבא Amar Rava נשבע על
כיכר ואכלה, nishba al kikar va-achala, you know what, let's not do
this, okay, because it gets us into a new topic. So we'll
pick up with this tomorrow.